This is the payment anomaly explainer, a machine learning pipeline I built to detect
suspicious wire transfers and automatically generated compliance explanations grounded
in the real payment regulations.
The app scores 500 synthetic ISO 2022 wire transfers using two models working together.
So these are the transactions and the two models are isolation or a switch flexor transaction
that looks statistically unusual compared to the rest of the data set.
Second an XG boost classifier that assigns a fraught probability score.
The combined risk score which is towards the extreme right column, this here is 0.97 out
of 1 which is extremely high at this.
What's interesting is the model is catching a pattern for structuring the transactions
are deliberately just under 20, the transactions are deliberately just in the $10,000 that's
significant because use regulation requires backstreet but any wire transfers over $10,000
to FinCEN which is the US financial crime regulator.
Criminals exploit this threshold to avoid detection and the model flags it automatically.
So now I will select the top, I will select the high risk and swift wire transaction here
in the drop down menu which is 090, over here it's 090.
The transaction details amount, the transaction details amount in the big codes, payment,
real time stamps and the model score of a matter end up ready which is sent to FAISS which
is a vector database built by meta.
FAISS has my entire compliance knowledge is stored as mathematical representation of
meaning.
This is like think of it like a smart search engine that understands the context not just
the keywords and when I hit click indeed compliance explanation it calls through the API of CROC
and here FAISS retrieves the two most relevant compliance rules for the specific transactions.
Those rules plus transaction details are passed into LLAMA, a.1 Meta's open source,
a large language model running free, running free through via a CROC API.
LLAMA reads both and writes the explanation like having the compliance and this available
instantly at zero cost.
Here's the output, it's citing rule number 002 for the transaction monitoring and giving
the compliance team a specific recommendation for the next step and also rule 003 as you
can see it's for structuring and threshold avoidance.
The compliance rules in my knowledge, the compliance rules in my knowledge are based
on the same ISO 2022 and cross body payment rates standards as I worked earlier one of
the via payment projects.
So every explanation is grounded in real payments domain knowledge and thanks for watching.